Leon Polk Smith
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Leon Polk Smith papers
1938-1997
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Smith, Leon Polk
7.2 linear feet
The papers of New York abstract painter Leon Polk Smith measure 7.2 linear feet and date from 1938 to 1997. The papers consist of biographical material, business and personal correspondence, interview transcripts and an interview video recording, writings, financial records for the corporate entity Leon Polk Smith, Inc., printed material, photographic material, and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings.
Provenance
The papers of Leon Polk Smith were donated by the artist's partner, Robert Jamieson, in 1998 and 2002.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2011 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. Blank pages, blank versos of photographs, photographs of artwork, duplicates, and medical and routine financial documents have not been scanned. In most cases, only the cover, title page, and individual relevant pages have been scanned from published materials.
The video recording in this collection was digitized for research access in 2011 and is available at the Archives of American Art offices. Researchers may view the original cassette for the archival notations on it, but the original cassette is not available for playback due to fragility.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Leon Polk Smith (1906-1996) worked primarily in New York City as a painter, educator, and lecturer. He is considered one of the founders of the hard edge style of minimalist abstract art.
Smith was born in Chickasha, Indian Territory one year before its formal incorporation into the Oklahoma Territory. Both of his parents were of Cherokee ancestry and he was raised in a small farming community that included Cherokee and Choctaw Indians. After receiving his teaching degree in 1934, Smith worked as an educator in rural Oklahoma communities and, at the same time, took the opportunity to introduce arts programs to local schools. In 1936, he enrolled in Columbia University's Teachers College to pursue a graduate degree in arts education and began painting full time. That summer, he visited the Albert E. Gallatin Gallery of Living Art at New York University, where he was first introduced to the work of the European modernists Constantin Brancusi, Jean Arp, and most importantly, Piet Mondrian.
In the late 1940s and early 1950s, Smith accepted university teaching positions at Rollins College in Florida, and New York University and Mills College of Education in New York. During this time, Smith moved beyond his early explorations of neo-plasticism and began to paint in a more hard edge style, typified by geometric lines, curving shapes of color, and the use of tondo (disk shaped) canvases. In 1958, Betty Parson's Section Eleven Gallery showcased his new work in two one-man exhibitions, which introduced him to a wider audience of museum curators and art collectors. In the 1960s, Smith's work was included in two of his most important group exhibitions, The Responsive Eye at the Museum of Modern Art (1965) and Systemic Painting at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum (1966). In 1995, the Brooklyn Museum curated Leon Polk Smith: American Painter, a retrospective exhibition of Smith's career.
Smith produced works exploring shapes and lines, minimalist use of color, and modularity well into the 1990s and exhibited at a number of affiliated galleries, including the Stable Gallery, Galerie Chalette, Galerie Denise Rene, Washburn Gallery, and ACA Galleries. Smith died in 1996 in his home in Manhattan, at the age of 91.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York abstract painter Leon Polk Smith measure 7.2 linear feet and date from 1938 to 1997. The papers consist of biographical material, business and personal correspondence, interview transcripts and an interview video recording, writings, financial records for the corporate entity Leon Polk Smith, Inc., printed material, photographic material, and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings.
Biographical material includes official affidavits, certificates, passports, expense receipts, and a travel expense notebook. A curriculum vitae, family history, and medical records are also included in the series.
Correspondence, both business and personal, comprises the bulk of the collection. This includes correspondence between Smith and his life companion, Robert Jamieson; art critics Arthur C. Danto, Claudine Humblet, and David Galloway; and artists Gego (Gertrude Goldschmidt) and Ray Johnson. Business correspondence relates to Smith's various gallery and museum exhibitions, loans, and sales. There is extensive correspondence between Smith and the Brooklyn Museum, Butler Institute of American Art, Di Laurenti Gallery, Edition and Galerie Hoffmann, Galerie Denise Rene, Meyers/Bloom Gallery, Washburn Gallery, and the Wilhelm-Hack Museum. The business subseries also includes correspondence between Smith and his alma mater, East Central University, formerly known as Oklahoma State University.
Interviews consist of six typewritten transcripts of interviews conducted with Smith over the course of his professional career from 1950 to 1993, a 1995 video interview of museum director Robert T. Buck discussing the Brooklyn Museum's exhibition of Leon Polk Smith for the television program National Arts, and a 1965 interview transcript with gallery owner Lucile Horsley.
Writings include sixteen published and unpublished scholarly essays on Smith and his work. The series also includes notes and a brief artist's statement by Smith regarding the pros and cons of modern art galleries.
Financial records are 1978-1989 federal income tax filings and routine tax preparation and payment receipts for the corporate entity Leon Polk Smith, Inc. Smith's personal filing records from 1987-1989 are also included in this series.
Printed material consists of two books, including the Brooklyn Museum's monograph Leon Polk Smith: American Painter, newspaper clippings reviewing Smith's work, and exhibition announcements and catalogs of Smith's museum and gallery shows from 1941 to 1997.
A scrapbook contains newspaper clippings documenting Smith's years as an educator and artist in Oklahoma in the 1930s and 1940s.
Photographs are of Smith and his acquaintances circa 1930-1960, and a representative selection of photographs and color slides of Smith's artwork from 1939 to 1960.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1938-1994 (Box 1, OV 10; 11 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1939-1997 (Boxes 1-5, 9, OV 10; 5 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, 1950-1995 (Boxes 5-6; 8 folders)
Series 4: Writings, 1963-1996 (Box 6; 13 folders)
Series 5: Financial Records, 1979-1990 (Box 6; 15 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1941-1997 (Boxes 6-7, 9; .5 linear feet)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1930-1940 (Box 8; 1 folder)
Series 8: Photographic Material, 1930-1990 (Box 8; 8 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art galleries, Commercial; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, Abstract -- United States
Types of Materials:
Essays; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Transcripts; Video recordings
Names:
Buck, Robert T.; Danto, Arthur Coleman, 1924-; Galloway, David D.; Gego; Humblet, Claudine, 1946-; Jamieson, Robert; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Brooklyn Museum; Butler Institute of American Art; East Central Oklahoma State University; Galerie Denise Rene; Meyers/Bloom Gallery; Washburn Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Wilhelm-Hack-Museum
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1938-1994, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 10; 11 folders)
  Biographical material includes official affidavits, certificates, passports, expense receipts, and a travel expense notebook. A curriculum vitae, family history, and medical records are also included in the series.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Affidavits, 1940, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Data, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1938, 1954, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medical Records, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1958-1973, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, Expenses, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Passports, 1939-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates, 1938, 1954, (Oversized material scanned with Box 1, F3) (Box OV 10)
- Correspondence1939-1996, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-5, 9, OV 10; 5 linear feet)
  Correspondence is predominantly in the form of business letters and personal letters received from family and friends. This includes correspondence between Smith and his life companion, Robert Jamieson; art critics Arthur C. Danto, Claudine Humblet, and David Galloway; and artists Gego (Gertrude Goldschmidt) and Ray Johnson.
  The bulk of the business correspondence relates to Smith's various gallery and museum exhibitions, loans, and sales. Outgoing correspondence, photographs, slides, and instructions on the installation of exhibitions have been chronologically interfiled within the correspondents' files. There is extensive correspondence between Smith and the Brooklyn Museum, Butler Institute of American Art, Di Laurenti Gallery, Edition and Galerie Hoffmann, Galerie Denise Rene, Meyers/Bloom Gallery, Washburn Gallery, and the Wilhelm-Hack Museum. The business subseries also includes correspondence between Smith and his alma mater, East Central University, formerly known as Oklahoma State University.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Slides of artwork filed with Meyers/Bloom Gallery have not been scanned. The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  Subseries 2.1: Business, 1943-1996
  Subseries 2.2: Personal, 1939-1997
  - Business, Subseries 2.1:
    - A, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ACE Gallery (Christmas, Douglas), 1979-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Albright-Knox Gallery, 1968, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Amarillo Art Center (Kochka, Al), 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Art and Literature, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Art Museum Association of America (Butera, Virginia), 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - B, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bard College, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brooklyn Museum, 1992-1995, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
    - Brooklyn Museum, 1995, (Oversized material housed in Box 9, F2) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Buecker, Robert, 1972-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Burnett Miller Gallery, 1984-1990, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Butler Institute of American Art, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - C, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Case Western Reserve University, 1969, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Ciba-Geigy Corporation, 1967-1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Columbia University, Wallach Gallery, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - D, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Daniel Goldreyer, Ltd., 1979-1992, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - Davis, Philip, 1981-1988, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - DiLaurenti Gallery, 1985-1989, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Dord Fitz Gallery, 1969-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - E, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - East Central University, 1984-1997, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
    - Edition and Galerie Hoffmann, circa 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Edition and Galerie Hoffmann, circa 1987-1993, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Edition and Galerie Hoffmann, 1987-1993, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
    - Elger, Dietmar, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - F-G, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - G.W. Einstein Company, Inc., 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Galerie Chalette, 1965-1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Galerie Denise Rene, 1971-1976, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Galerie Denise Rene, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Galerie Muller, 1964-1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Gallery North, 1976-1981, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Gallery of Applied Arts, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gallery Paule Anglim, 1970, 1979-1981, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Gibson, Ann, 1990-1991, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Goethe-Institut (Osaka and Turin), 1987-1992, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Gorewitz, Rubin, 1981-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Grace Borgenicht Gallery, 1981-1983, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Guggenheim Museum, 1970-1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Guild Hall, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - H, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Heckscher Museum, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hoffman, Marianne, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - I, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - International Contemporary Art Fair (Robinson, Charles), 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - J, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - James Lodge and Associates, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - K, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Kunstverein in Hamburg, 1989, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - L, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - La Paloma (McPherson, Ronald and Morikawa, Mark), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - M, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Marilyn Pearl Gallery, 1980-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Meyers/Bloom Gallery, 1988-1993, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
    - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Musee de Grenoble, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Musee National D'Art Moderne, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Texas, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - N, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Nabakowski, Gislind, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - National Galerie Berlin (Grisebach, Lucius), 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Nurnberg Museum, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - O, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Oklahoma City Art Museum, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - P, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Pelham-von Stoffler Gallery, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Prakapas Gallery, 1986-1993 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - R, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - R+V Allgemeine Versicherung AG (Weiermair, Peter), 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Riley, Orrin H., 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - S, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Sidney Janis Gallery, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Siegel Contemporary Art Inc./Ruth Siegel Ltd., 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation (Rebay, Hilla), 1943-1949 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Squatriti, Fausta/La Biennale di Venezia, 1982-1991 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Stamford Museum and Nature Center, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - SUNY, College At Old Westbury, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Susan Caldwell Gallery, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - T, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Tallix, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - U, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - University of Oklahoma, Museum of Art, 1971-1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - V, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Volair Gallery, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - W, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Washburn Gallery, 1980-1985, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1964, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Wichita State University, 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Wilhelm-Hack Museum, circa 1988-1995, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Wilhelm-Hack Museum, 1988-1995, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
    - Y, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Yale University Art Gallery, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Brooklyn Museum, Draft Exhibition Catalog, 1995, (Scanned with Box 1, F22) (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Edition and Galerie Hoffmann, Exhibition Announcements, circa 1987-1993, (Scanned with Box 2, F10) (Box OV 10)
    - Galerie Denise Rene, Artwork Layout, 1976, (Scanned with Box 2, F20) (Box OV 10)
    - Goethe-Institut, Color Sample, circa 1987-1992, (Scanned with Box 2, F27) (Box OV 10)
    - Grace Borgenicht Gallery, Gallery Floor Plan, 1981, (Scanned with Box 3, F2) (Box OV 10)
    - Kunstverein in Hamburg, Gallery Floor Plan, 1989, (Scanned with Box 3, F13) (Box OV 10)
    - Wilhelm-Hack Museum, Gallery Floor Plan, circa 1988-1995, (Scanned with Box 4, F13) (Box OV 10)
  - Personal, Subseries 2.2:
    - A, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - B, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Buck, Bob, 1992-1996 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Butera, Virginia, 1984-1995 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - C, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Clark, Alma, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - D, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Danto, Arthur C., 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Downe, Edward Jr., 1980-1982, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - E, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - F, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - G, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Galloway, David, 1981-1993 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Gego, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Glattfelder, Hans, 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - H, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Highwater, Jamake, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Humblet, Claudine, 1985-1989, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
    - Humblet, Claudine, 1990-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - I, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Inaya, Beata, 1969-1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - J, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - K, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Kennedy, Edward M., 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - L, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Little, John, 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - M, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - N, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - O, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - P, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Parks, Addison, 1982-1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Pekarsky, Melvin, 1980-1989, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
    - Polk, Mark, 1990-1996, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
    - R, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Rowe, Harry L., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - S, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Smith, Leon Polk and Jamieson, Robert, 1968-1972, (Oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Smith, Leon Polk and Jamieson, Robert, 1981-1994 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Smith, Virginia, 1969-1996 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - T, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - V, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Vavruska, Frank, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - W, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Walls, Michael, 1979-1984, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Warren, Alice, 1968-1976, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Wooding, Robert, 1987-1995 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Workman, David, 1984-1988 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Y-Z, Miscellaneous, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified and Illegible, circa 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Smith, Leon Polk, Oversized Lettercirca 1968-1972, (Scanned with Box 5, F23) (Box OV 10)
- Interviews, 1950-1995, Series 3:; (Boxes 5-6; 8 folders)
  Interviews consist of six typewritten transcripts of interviews conducted with Smith from 1950 to 1993 by Brooke Kamin Rapaport, D'Arcy Hayman, and William Jeffett, among others, over the course of Smith's professional career. The series also includes a 1995 video interview of museum director Robert T. Buck discussing the Brooklyn Museum's exhibition of Leon Polk Smith for the television program National Arts, and a 1965 interview transcript with gallery owner Lucile Horsley.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety. The video interview recording has been digitized for research access and is available at the Archives of American Art offices.
  - Creative Art Seminar Symposium on Modern Art, March 1950 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - K. Osis Interview of Leon Polk Smith, May-June 1963 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - D'Arcy Hayman Interview of Leon Polk Smith, May 1964 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Gerald Moore Interview of Lucile Horsley, March 1965 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - William Jeffet Interview of Leon Polk Smith, May 1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - James Collins Interview of Leon Polk Smith, November 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Brooke Kamin Rapaport Interview of Leon Polk Smith, July 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Michael Baker Interview of Robert T Buck for National Arts, 1995, (Video recording) (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1963-1996, Series 4:; (Box 6; 13 folders)
  Writings include sixteen published and unpublished scholarly essays on Smith by Lawrence Alloway, Ted Castle, Arthur C. Danto, Carter Ratcliff, and Joseph R. Wolin, among others. The series also includes notes and a brief artist's statement by Smith regarding the pros and cons of modern art galleries.
  - "Constellations", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Alloway, Lawrence, Four Essays, 1963, 1970, 1974, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Calas, Nicholas, "Leon Polk Smith, The Pioneer", 1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Castle, Ted, "Leon Polk Smith: The Completely Self-Referential Object", 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Danto, Arthur C., "Painting as Sculpture: Leon Polk Smith and Real Space", 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Elger, Dietmar, "Leon Polk Smith - An Introduction", circa 1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Parks, Addison, "Leon Polk Smith", 1992, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Ratcliff, Carter, Three Essays, 1971, 1987, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Seeman, Joan, "Leon Polk Smith", 1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Smith, Leon Polk, "Minus Gallery/Plus Gallery", 1965 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Leon Polk, Notes, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Walsh, Grace M., "Leon Polk Smith: A Pioneering Geometric Abstractionist", 1995 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Wolin, Joseph R., "Line Forms Space", 1994 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Financial Records, 1979-1990, Series 5:; (Box 6; 15 folders)
  Financial records is comprised of the 1978-1989 federal income tax filings and routine tax preparation and payment receipts for the corporate entity Leon Polk Smith, Inc. Smith's personal filing records from 1987-1989 are also included in this series.
  This series has not been scanned.
  - Corporate Taxes, 1978-1989 Federal Filing Forms, 1979-1990 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1978 Preparation, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1979 Preparation, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1980 Preparation, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1981 Preparation, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1982 Preparation, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1983 Preparation, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1984 Preparation, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Corporate Taxes, 1985 Preparation, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 26)